<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: bertrand russell | Notes to self]]></title>
  <link href="http://pastafari.github.com/blog/categories/bertrand-russell/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pastafari.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-07-31T00:13:09+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://pastafari.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mohit Thatte]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ten Commandments from Bertrand Russell]]></title>
    <link href="http://pastafari.github.com/blog/2012/05/08/ten-commandments-from-bertrand-russell/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-08T12:29:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://pastafari.github.com/blog/2012/05/08/ten-commandments-from-bertrand-russell</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I stumbled upon an
<a href="http://www.brainpickings.org/index.php/2012/05/02/a-liberal-decalogue-bertrand-russell/">interesting article</a>
about Bertrand Russell's philosophy. Here is a 'Note to self' that is
probably going to be one of the foundations of my lifes philosophy!</p>

<blockquote><p>Perhaps the essence of the Liberal outlook could be summed up in a new decalogue, not intended to replace the old one but only to supplement it. The Ten Commandments that, as a teacher, I should wish to promulgate, might be set forth as follows:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Do not feel absolutely certain of anything.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Do not think it worth while to proceed by concealing evidence, for the evidence is sure to come to light.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Never try to discourage thinking for you are sure to succeed.</strong></li>
<li><strong>When you meet with opposition, even if it should be from your husband or your children, endeavor to overcome it by argument and not by authority, for a victory dependent upon authority is unreal and illusory.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Have no respect for the authority of others, for there are always contrary authorities to be found.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Do not use power to suppress opinions you think pernicious, for if you do the opinions will suppress you.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Do not fear to be eccentric in opinion, for every opinion now accepted was once eccentric.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Find more pleasure in intelligent dissent than in passive agreement, for, if you value intelligence as you should, the former implies a deeper agreement than the latter.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Be scrupulously truthful, even if the truth is inconvenient, for it is more inconvenient when you try to conceal it.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Do not feel envious of the happiness of those who live in a fool’s paradise, for only a fool will think that it is happiness.</strong></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
